do you remember what your hands can do
grab a needle and thread
and let's sew together
let's practice our back stitching and
for this tutorial i'm going to be doing
the type of backstitch that touches one
another that essentially looks like it's
been done with the sewing machine so to
begin i've already pinned my fabric so
what you're looking at is essentially
you'd pin your fabric so that it's right
sides together so i've drawn a line on
my fabric as a guideline and that's
something i would really recommend to
to anyone practicing because that way
you don't have to really think about
where is the needle headed all you have
to do is follow that line
so if you're right-handed you're going
to stitch right to left if you are
left-handed you're going to be stitching
left to right
i'm going to start a stitch with the way
from this edge i'm going to pick up my
fabric and i'm going to take my needle
and from the underside
push my needle perpendicular through the
fabric again about a stitch
away from the edge of where i want that
stitch to start i'm going to push that
needle up again perpendicular pulling it
until the knot locks in place
and now i'm going to start going truly
back so i'm going to go back to where
that stitch is going to begin
i'm going to dip my needle down to the
fabric
and then i'm going to progress forward
on the other side of that tail
and so this is what your stitch is going
to look like we're not stab stitching
we're going to make sure that this
needle is in essence parallel
to
the fabric as we're working and then
parallel to our bodies as we're working
and a trick to making sure your stitches
are even
is make sure that wherever your tail is
is in essence
bisecting the
distance between where your needle is
going into the fabric and then where
that needle is coming out of the fabric
so i'm going to push this through of
course using my my thimble to finally
kind of push that needle through so i've
done one stitch and now i'm going to go
back to the stitch that i just did
you can put it through the same hole you
can put it right next to the hole
you may even put it just slightly
underneath that hole
i've seen kind of all of those done on
historical clothes
i'm going to push this down through the
fabric
and then gently kind of rock it up
again that same distance
that tail is going to bisect the
distance between where the needle comes
out and where the needle goes in
pushing it through picking it up again
now laying in that other stitch and
we're just going to continue
to stitch down the length of this fabric
i want to remind you as always to keep
your hands nice and relaxed
make sure that you're sitting up
straight
make sure the work is at your navel
height because either your feet are
elevated you they're on a pillow or on
the table
and as we're working we're going to want
to make sure that we're pulling this
tight enough
that it sets
the stitch into the fabric
not so tight that it really
gathers it but if it's too loose
it's not going to set in the seam
correctly the back side looks like this
it's actually a loop
going back on itself and that loop makes
this an extremely strong stitch so i
definitely recommend this for like
underarm seams
any seam that's going to have stress on
it your back stitch is definitely going
to be your friend
now i recommend doing about eight to ten
stitches per inch because that's going
to be nice and strong for the purposes
of the back stitch
and honestly just keep practicing you
want to make sure that your stitches are
even you want to make sure that it's
tight enough so that the tension is good
and keeping your hands parallel to the
work the needle parallel to the the
fabric
and just enjoy the process of really
mastering your back stitch
to knot off your stitching line go as
though you are making one more stitch
so put your needle dip it down to the
fabric
next to that stitch but instead of
progressing forward we're just going to
push our needle down perpendicular to
the other side of the material
pull it through
and then flip over the work
then i'm going to take a tiny bite out
of the fabric and the thread underneath
it here
i'm going to take a stitch
and instead of pulling it all the way
through i'm going to keep a loop there
and then i'm going to put my needle
through that loop
twice and then i'm going to go ahead and
put my needle
between the stitches and the fabric
and this is going to be perpendicular
through the thread and through
the stitching
just to kind of hide the tail
and then you can go ahead and clip that
off
and there you have it
a back stitch from the back and then a
nice back stitch from the front
keep practicing i look forward to seeing
your sewing
you